An ancient, crumbling document lets the present know about an old anecdote.
It talks about the existence of a huge stone believed to be the root of Mega Evolution.
The setting of the adventure revolving around Mega Evolution...
...now shifts to the Houen region.
The Strongest Mega Evolution ~Act II~
Hurry, hurry! This way, this way!
I'm fine! Let's go!
While watching anime, make sure not to sit too close to the screen and that the room is well lit.
It's around here.
Manon!
Alan!
My butt is stuck! I can't get my butt out!
Huh?
Are you all right?
Heave-ho!
Play a board game via the Pocket Monsters XY data broadcast!
Press the d-button on your remote and try reaching the battles and the presents!!
Thank you very much.
My name is Manon. I've come from the Kalos region.
Nice to meet you!
Oh wow... Welcome to the faraway Houen.
I'm Daigo. Nice to meet you.
Daigo-san!
Though why have you come to such a remote place?
Uhm...
Are you all right, Manon?
Yeah. Daigo-san helped me.
This is my travelmate Alan and my partner Hari-san.
Thank you.
A Key Stone...
You have one, too.
Will you battle me?
It might not look like it, but I'm quite busy.
It won't take long.
I'll defeat all Mega Evolutions and stand at the top.
If you're a Pokémon Trainer, you know that eye contact is the cue for a battle, right?
You've got a point.
Manon, step back.
Yeah.
Go, Lizardon!
I see. A Lizardon, huh?
So then, here's my partner...
Metagross!
So Metagross can mega evolve too.
It's an alternate-colored Metagross, Hari-san!
But aren't Steel types weak against Fire types?
Let's go, Lizardon!
Respond to my heart,
Key Stone!
Surpass evolution!
Mega Evolution!
Flamethrower!
Psychic!
The sparkle of the stone...
...shall be our bond!
Metagross,
mega evolve!
So cool!
Flash Cannon!
Flash Cannon's secondary effect has lowered Lizardon's stamina.
In that case, we'll defeat it before it defeats us!
Dragon Claw!
Meteor Mash!
It's so fast!
Mega Evolution allows Metagross's speed to dramatically increase.
Oh, not bad!
Take this...
Blast Burn!
It endured it.
No way! And it was a direct hit, too!
Please don't underestimate my Metagross.
Dragon Claw!
Meteor Mash!
What?
A Kaenjishi?
Could it be...?
Can you put the battle on hold for a moment?
Director!
Who is that?
Please excuse my subordinate's rudeness,
Champion.
"Champion"?
This is Daigo-san, the Champion of the Houen region's Pokémon League.
Hari-san, that voice...
Excuse me, but you are...?
I'm sorry for not introducing myself earlier.
My name is Fleur-de-lis; I represent the Fleur-de-lis Labs in the Kalos region.
I'm having him investigate Mega Evolution.
Investigate...
Hey, hey!
Are you the one who called Alan from time to time?
Hm?
Manon!
Who is this girl, Alan?
I'm Manon! This is Hari-san, the most capable Pokémon in Kalos.
And see, me and Alan are currently doing extremely well!
That's quite a small girlfriend you got yourself there.
Uh...
Non, non! I'm not his girlfriend. I just want to mega evolve, too!
Again, it's the Pokémon that mega evolves, not you.
I know that.
Never mind. Go somewhere else.
I've got something important to discuss.
Hmph! What's with you, treating me like a child all the time?
Non, non, non!
Geez, you're always like this...
Hang on!
You said earlier that you were having him "investigate"...
Yes.
The truth is, at my Fleur-de-lis Labs, we focus on the energy emitted by Pokémon when they mega evolve and collect data on it.
Through the Mega Ring he is wearing, that is.
The energy from Mega Evolutions is immense.
We're conducting research on whether it could be used for peaceful purposes.
Peaceful purposes, you say...
By the way, Champion,
do you know this?
That's...
Hey, hey, Alan. Who's Fleur-de-lis-san?
He's very important to me.
More than Professor Platane, even?
Look, Professor! Hitokage has evolved!
Wow, congratulations, Alan, Lizardo!
I don't have nothing but good news, though...
You're referring to the Mega Evolution stone, right?
Yes. But I won't give up!
I've gained information on some other ruins.
I'll go and have a look.
Nothing here either...
Excuse me.
Is this what you're looking for?
That's...!
...a Denryunite. I've been looking for this as well.
If you really want it, you can claim it by winning a battle.
Let's go, Lizardo!
If you want to fulfill your wish, become the greatest.
Pokémon discharge powerful energy upon mega evolving.
This power is immense and I'm conducting research on whether it could be used for peaceful purposes.
In that case, let Professor Platane assist you...
I can't do that.
If he publishes the information, there will be people who want to use it for bad purposes.
One look at human history and you'll see it's inevitable.
We can't let such people sully the professor like that!
He needs to be protected!
Protect the professor...
So I want to ask...
Will you assist me?
It's a Key Stone and a Lizardonite.
Th-These...
If you want to fulfill your wish, become the greatest.
Alan! Hey, Alan!
Fleur-de-lis-san is leaving.
Coming up next:
Finally, that Pokémon appears...!
This program is brought to you by these sponsors.
How will the greatest Mega battle go!?
Director, this place is...
Probably.
I'm sorry to keep you waiting.
I've been traveling looking for various stones,
but ever since I came to know of the existence of Mega Evolution, I've been searching for its roots.
What does "roots" mean?
It means "foundation".
What does "foundation" mean?
Look at this.
This is mine.
I figured you had one...
It's the wooden tablet referencing the legendary megalith...
This is what lead us to come to this region as well.
Oh, it's the same!
No, it's different from mine.
The tablet was split into several pieces, each having differing contents.
Wow...
If we combine the pieces of information each of us has...
...we can come even closer to the answer.
Looks like we ought to work together.
According to this wooden tablet, the ancient people were in the possession of a legendary megalith.
The text has been deciphered as, "The path to the megalith begins with the gate."
Mine says, "The key to opening the gate is the glimmer of two stones."
"When those stones come together, a new path will appear."
Key Stones?
That's it!
Yes.
Please follow me.
I see.
Yes... This is believed to be the gate.
Whoa, it's so high up!
Alan, step over there.
Whoa, amazing!
I'm floored, Fleur-de-lis-san.
If you hadn't come, I would've been digging holes here forever.
No, I have to thank you.
Also, Alan.
Without you, this path wouldn't have been born.
I'm grateful.
The Champion is grateful to you!
Aren't you something?
Now then, let's go.
Here it is...
The megalith must be somewhere around here.
"Hold different keys over the two altars."
There's no doubt; the megalith is here.
Alan, go to the other altar.
Got it.
Hold your Key Stone out.
We've found the legendary megalith!
The roots of Mega Evolution.
The Key Stone is reacting to it.
Hm...
It's me. We've discovered it.
We've already got a hold of your coordinates, Director. We'll be there shortly.
Non, non! Hari-san, it's dangerous.
What's the meaning of this?
We will first analyze its components.
After all, it's a valuable discovery.
The energy of this light has the same wavelength as a Mega Stone.
Not only that, but its calorific value surpasses that of a Mega Stone by a large margin.
What?!
Something's coming!
What's that?
Rayquaza?
Director, the inner pressure of the megalith is increasing more than we expected!
Rayquaza can mega evolve?
No way...
But it's happening for real.
Wh-What?
That's...
Watch out! Everyone, run!
Have we enraged Rayquaza?
Step back.
Y-Yeah...
Go, Lizardon!
Let's go, Metagross!
Mega evolve!
Flamethrower!
Be careful, Lizardon!
What is this...?
Catch it, Metagross!
Oh no, that's Draco Meteor!
Manon!
Is it trying to destroy this place?
Are you all right?
Uh, yeah...
We're fine.
Thank you.
Alan!
What's the matter?
It's nothing bad.
You're lying! You looked like you were in big pain.
Never mind. Where is the megalith?
It's gone?
Are Rayquaza and the megalith related in some way?
Energy waves?
Yeah. They've been detected on the coast of Kanazumi City, if only feebly.
Their undulation and the undulation detected from the megalith match in form.
Kanazumi City?
So will we be able to locate the disappeared megalith?
The chances are high.
We will follow it non-stop.
Alan... Please go to Kanazumi City to investigate.
Understood.
I'll go, too.
Okay.
I'll arrange for someone to collect us immediately.
Also, Alan.
Yes?
Don't let the Champion out of your sight.
His knowledge will prove to be of great help to us.
I won't!
Humanity has an everlasting desire for knowledge about Mega Evolution.
In time, this desire may bring about...
...great change for both people and Pokémon.
Mega evolving Pokémon we do not yet know of,
I ask you to show yourselves before us!
We are waiting...